Data Base theory

1.Introduction

A database is a centralized data repository which collects, stocks data, and organizes data in order to improve the consultation.

With time, different types of database has been proposed:

Tree (1960s, relation 1 to N, simple structure but inflexible)

Network model (1970s, relation N to M, a flexible way of representing objects and their relationships, COmmon Business Oriented Language aka. cobol)

Relational (N to M.Developed by IBM and proposed by Dr Edgar Codd in the 1970s, it was built on mathematics -Relational Algebra. No redundant data (save storage), Strong consistency, No data loss: the relation set represents the whole data set.)

object-oriented (1980s, replaced by ORM frameworks)

Multi-dimensional (1990s, often used in Business intelligence)

NoSQL (2003,came in with big data ecosystem: four types: Key-Value store, Document store, Graph store, Column store)

NewSQL (2011, NoSQL with acid (strong transactional check), newest solution: Google Spanner (successor of BigTable), VoltDB,H-Store).)

2.Terminologies

2.1 Transaction

What is a transaction in a database?

Each transaction is an operation set (Data Management Language) performed on data

2.2 OLTP

On-Line Transactional Processing ( OLTP )

3. Relational database

A relational database:

manages transaction: Multi insert, delete, update simultaneously

provides a high transaction concurrency level.

introduce the normal form

3.1 Four properties of a relational database

Atomic

Each transaction is an operation set (DML) performed on data which is efficient when the transaction had been validated.

The database handles the transaction, as a unit, which can be validated or canceled.

In case of failure, all DML in a transaction is canceled.

Consistency

Any valid or canceled transaction change the data status from one valid status to another valid status

The transaction should be based on the business rules.

In case of money transfers from account A into account B: money is not created or destroyed but moved only and the credited amount should be the same as the debited one

Isolation

All transactions are running as if each one is the only one executed by the system.

Transactions control all accesses through a secure mechanism. When data are modified by a transaction, they are locked and can not be changed by another transaction.

Through the « read consistency » mechanism displayed by the RDBMS, a transaction t1 can overlook the

current modifications by a transaction t2 just before t1

Durability

Once the transaction is validated all data are stored and accessible to all users

Any data change is done through a transaction

Bilan / Action

1. Les tickets papiers sont à reporter dans Redmine comme demandes ou sous demande de Features

2. Shibboleth :

la partie Symfony sera disponible après commit.

la partie Shibboleth est en cours (problème de communication/filtrage/débuggage)

3. Utilisateur / permission / site / labo

création de la page de profil utilisateur

création du mode connecté / déconnecté

4. Echantillon

Documentation en cours du CRUD

Design suffisamment pour commencer.

Classification

* Echantillon : BioSpecimens doit tendre vers les normes SNOMED et NOINK/NOINC. * Bioentity : reprendre la taxonomy du NCBI pour remmplir la DB, mais afficher une classifcation simplifiée pour l'utilisateur. * Reactifs, équipements, logiciels, :

Reactifs : réutiliser les catégories du catalogue Sigma/Thermo/etc.? Demander à Pauline chez qui on commande le plus (+ un catalogue)? En fait, non, la classification des réactifs est celle des process.

Equipements/Instruments : Technologie (Mass Spec, Sequençage…) > Fabriquant (Brucker, Thermo…)

Logiciels : Technologie (analyse stat, assemblage de génome…)

* Fichiers: la classification des fichiers est celle des process. * Process : A définir.

Stages UTEC6

Création d'un projet Redmine par stagiaire dans la catégorie Stage UTEC6

A faire : Gantt de chaque stagiaire + Sujet du stage sur le Wiki.

Install and configure elasticsearch and kibana

What is ElasticSearch

Initially released in 2010, Elasticsearch is a modern search and analytics engine which is based on Apache Lucene. Completely open source and built with Java, Elasticsearch is categorized as a NoSQL database. That means it stores data in an unstructured way and that you cannot use SQL to query it.

Unlike most NoSQL databases, though, Elasticsearch has a strong focus on search capabilities and features so much so, in fact, that the easiest way to get data from Elasticsearch is to search for it using its extensive REST API.

ElasticSearch General feautres

Elasticsearch is scalable up to petabytes of structured and unstructured data.

Elasticsearch can be used as a replacement of document stores like MongoDB and RavenDB.

Elasticsearch uses denormalization to improve the search performance.

Elasticsearch is one of the popular enterprise search engines, which is currently being used by many big organizations like Wikipedia, The Guardian, StackOverflow, GitHub etc.

Elasticsearch is open source and available under the Apache license version 2.0.

Key concepts

Node − It refers to a single running instance of Elasticsearch. Single physical and virtual server accommodates multiple nodes depending upon the capabilities of their physical resources like RAM, storage and processing power.

Cluster − It is a collection of one or more nodes. Cluster provides collective indexing and search capabilities across all the nodes for entire data.

Index − It is a collection of different type of documents and document properties. Index also uses the concept of shards to improve the performance. For example, a set of document contains data of a social networking application.

Type/Mapping − It is a collection of documents sharing a set of common fields present in the same index. For example, an Index contains data of a social networking application, and then there can be a specific type for user profile data, another type for messaging data and another for comments data.

Document − It is a collection of fields in a specific manner defined in JSON format. Every document belongs to a type and resides inside an index. Every document is associated with a unique identifier, called the UID.

Shard − Indexes are horizontally subdivided into shards. This means each shard contains all the properties of document, but contains less number of JSON objects than index. The horizontal separation makes shard an independent node, which can be store in any node. Primary shard is the original horizontal part of an index and then these primary shards are replicated into replica shards.

Replicas − Elasticsearch allows a user to create replicas of their indexes and shards. Replication not only helps in increasing the availability of data in case of failure, but also improves the performance of searching by carrying out a parallel search operation in these replicas.

Advantage and disadvantage

Advantage :

Elasticsearch is developed on Java, which makes it compatible on almost every platform.

Elasticsearch is real time, in other words after one second the added document is searchable in this engine.

Elasticsearch is distributed, which makes it easy to scale and integrate in any big organization.

Creating full backups are easy by using the concept of gateway, which is present in Elasticsearch.

Handling multi-tenancy is very easy in Elasticsearch when compared to Apache Solr.

Elasticsearch uses JSON objects as responses, which makes it possible to invoke the Elasticsearch server with a large number of different programming languages.

Elasticsearch supports almost every document type except those that do not support text rendering.

Disadvantage :

Elasticsearch does not have multi-language support in terms of handling request and response data (only possible in JSON) unlike in Apache Solr, where it is possible in CSV, XML and JSON formats.

Elasticsearch also have a problem of Split brain situations, but in rare cases.

Comparison between ElasticSearch and RDBMS

Elasticsearch | RDBMS
Index | Database
Shard | Shard
Mapping | Table
Field | Field
JSON Object | Tuple

Install elasticsearch

All the following installation guide is tested on centos7.

Pre-requise : JDK 1.8 +. Folllow this tutorial to install JDK : Install oracle jdk on ubuntu 16.04

You have many option to install it, Please go see here : https://www.elastic.co/downloads/elasticsearch

In a prod environment, it's better to use rpm to install it.

In our case, we just use the tar ball of the current stable version (elasticsearch-6.1.3.tar.gz).

Download elasticsearch tar ball and put it in /opt/elasticsearch/ and unzip it.

After you finish this, it should looks like this.

[root@localhost elasticsearch-6.1.3]# pwd
/opt/elasticsearch/elasticsearch-6.1.3
[root@localhost elasticsearch-6.1.3]# ls
bin  config  lib  LICENSE.txt  logs  modules  NOTICE.txt  plugins  README.textile

Configure ElasticSearch

Elasticsearch configurations are done using a configuration file that is located in different locations depending on your operating system. There are too main config files, elasticsearch.yml and jvm.options. In elasticsearch.yml, you can configure general settings (e.g. node name), as well as network settings (e.g. host and port), where data is stored. In jvm.options you can configure jvm heap memory and more.

For development and testing purposes, the default settings will suffice yet it is recommended you do some research into what settings can be manually defined before going into production.

Single node ElasticSearch config

For example, and especially if installing Elasticsearch on the cloud, it is a good practice to bind Elasticsearch to either a private IP or localhost:

The following elasticsearch.yml is an example

# ---------------------------------- Cluster -----------------------------------
#
# Use a descriptive name for your cluster:
#
cluster.name: hdfs_elastic
#
# ------------------------------------ Node ------------------------------------
#
# Use a descriptive name for the node:
#
node.name: node-1
#
# Add custom attributes to the node:
#
node.attr.rack: r1
#
# ----------------------------------- Paths ------------------------------------
#
# Path to directory where to store the data (separate multiple locations by comma):
#
path.data: /tmp/elastic/data
#
# Path to log files:
#
path.logs: /tmp/elastic/logs
#
# ----------------------------------- Memory -----------------------------------
#
# Lock the memory on startup:
#
#bootstrap.memory_lock: true
#
# Make sure that the heap size is set to about half the memory available
# on the system and that the owner of the process is allowed to use this
# limit.
#
# Elasticsearch performs poorly when the system is swapping the memory.

Run the elasticsearch service

If you install it via tar bar as I do. go to elastic home, (/opt/elasticsearch/elasticsearch-6.1.3/), and run

./bin/elasticsearch

Common problems of installation

File descriptors limitation

After run the elasticsearch, if you see the following errors

ERROR: [1] bootstrap checks failed
[1]: max file descriptors [4096] for elasticsearch process is too low, increase to at least [65536]

you need to reset the process open file limitation at /etc/security/limits.conf. The default value depends on your linux distribution (e.g. centos7 4096, ubuntu 65536)

# a woring example 
# * means for everyone, if you want to set limit for a user just put uid (e.g. pliu)
# if you want to set limit for a group just put @gid(e.g. @hadoop)
#        - "soft" for enforcing the soft limits
#        - "hard" for enforcing hard limits
# nofile - number of file

* hard nofile 65536
* soft nofile 65536

Check the maximum open files

#1. get the elastic process id
ps -u elasticsearch
#output:
PID TTY          TIME CMD
11708 ?        00:00:10 java

#2. get the max open file numbers
cat /proc/11708/limits | grep 'Max open files'

#output: 
Max open files            65535                65535                files

max virtual memory areas

if you see the following errors

[2]: max virtual memory areas vm.max_map_count [65530] is too low, increase to at least [262144]

You need to do reset the max virtual memory areas

sysctl -w vm.max_map_count=262144

Multi node ElasticSearch cluster config

Elastic search has build in cluster mode. So it's really easy to build to elastic search cluster

In this example, we suppose we have 3 server cluster

IP | URI | elastic_node_name
10.70.3.48 | hadoop-nn.bioaster.org | node-1
10.70.3.49 | hadoop-dn1.bioaster.org | node-2
10.70.3.50 | hadoop-dn2.bioaster.org | node-3

Install the elasticsearch tar ball as above. Configure the elasticsearch.yml for each node

# ---------------------------------- Cluster -----------------------------------
#
# Use a descriptive name for your cluster: 
# It must be the same for the 3 node
cluster.name: hdfs_elastic
#
# ------------------------------------ Node ------------------------------------
#
# Use a descriptive name for the node:
# node name must be unique inside the cluster
# in our example, it will be node-1, node-2, node-3
node.name: node-1
#
# Add custom attributes to the node:
#
#node.attr.rack: r1
#
# ----------------------------------- Paths ------------------------------------
#
# Path to directory where to store the data (separate multiple locations by comma):
#
path.data: /tmp/elastic/data
#
# Path to log files:
#
path.logs: /tmp/elastic/logs
#
# ----------------------------------- Memory -----------------------------------
#
# Lock the memory on startup:
#
#bootstrap.memory_lock: true
#
# Make sure that the heap size is set to about half the memory available
# on the system and that the owner of the process is allowed to use this
# limit.
#
# Elasticsearch performs poorly when the system is swapping the memory.
#
# ---------------------------------- Network -----------------------------------
#
# Set the bind address to a specific IP (IPv4 or IPv6):
# The network host should be the ip address or uri of the node
# This will force elastic search only answer request from this uri or ip address
# This is also security concern. the elasticsearch is completely
# driven by rest api without any security. The ip address must be protected (private ip or vpn ) 
# which can be accessed only by trusted people and service
# Do not bind Elasticsearch to a public or shared private network IP address!
# Note the addition of "_local_", which configures Elasticsearch to also listen on all loopback devices
# such as localhost or 127.0.0.1
network.host: [10.70.3.48,_local_]
#
# Set a custom port for HTTP:
#
http.port: 9200
#
# For more information, consult the network module documentation.
#
# --------------------------------- Discovery ----------------------------------
#
# Pass an initial list of hosts to perform discovery when new node is started:
# The default list of hosts is ["127.0.0.1", "[::1]"]
# In this line we put uri or ip address of all the nodes in the elastic cluster.
discovery.zen.ping.unicast.hosts: ["hadoop-nn.bioaster.org", "hadoop-dn1.bioaster.org","hadoop-dn2.bioaster.org"]
#
# Prevent the "split brain" by configuring the majority of nodes (total number of master-eligible nodes / 2 + 1):
#
#discovery.zen.minimum_master_nodes: 
#
# For more information, consult the zen discovery module documentation.

Dedicated Master nodes and data nodes

There are two common types of Elasticsearch nodes: master and data. Master nodes perform cluster-wide actions, such as managing indices and determining which data nodes should store particular data shards. Data nodes hold shards of your indexed documents, and handle CRUD, search, and aggregation operations. As a general rule, data nodes consume a significant amount of CPU, memory, and I/O.

By default, every Elasticsearch node is configured to be a “master-eligible” data node, which means they store data (and perform resource-intensive operations) and have the potential to be elected as a master node. For a small cluster, this is usually fine; a large Elasticsearch cluster, however, should be configured with dedicated master nodes so that the master node's stability can't be compromised by intensive data node work.

How to Configure Dedicated Master Nodes

Before configuring dedicated master nodes, ensure that your cluster will have at least 3 master-eligible nodes. This is important to avoid a split-brain situation, which can cause inconsistencies in your data in the event of a network failure.

#For master node, edit the elasticsearch.yml
node.master: true 
node.data: false

#for data node 
node.master: false 
node.data: true

Configure Minimum Master Nodes

When running an Elasticsearch cluster, it is important to set the minimum number of master-eligible nodes that need to be running for the cluster to function normally, which is sometimes referred to as quorum. This is to ensure data consistency in the event that one or more nodes lose connectivity to the rest of the cluster, preventing what is known as a “split-brain” situation.

To calculate the number of minimum master nodes your cluster should have, calculate n / 2 + 1, where n is the total number of “master-eligible” nodes in your healthy cluster, then round the result down to the nearest integer. For example, for a 3-node cluster, the quorum is 2.

Note: Be sure to include all master-eligible nodes in your quorum calculation, including any data nodes that are master-eligible (default setting).

The minimum master nodes setting can be set dynamically, through the Elasticsearch HTTP API. To do so, run this command on any node (replace the highlighted number with your quorum):

# use curl to request rest api
curl -XPUT localhost:9200/_cluster/settings?pretty -d '{
    "persistent" : {
        "discovery.zen.minimum_master_nodes" : 2
    }
}'

#output

{
  "acknowledged" : true,
  "persistent" : {
    "discovery" : {
      "zen" : {
        "minimum_master_nodes" : "2"
      }
    }
  },
  "transient" : { }
}

Enable Memory Locking

Elastic recommends to avoid swapping the Elasticsearch process at all costs, due to its negative effects on performance and stability. One way avoid excessive swapping is to configure Elasticsearch to lock the memory that it needs.

Complete this step on all of your Elasticsearch servers.

sudo vim elasticsearch.yml

bootstrap.mlockall: true

sudo vim jvm.options 

# Xms represents the initial size of total heap space
# Xmx represents the maximum size of total heap space

-Xms2g
-Xmx4g

Verify the memory lock status

curl http://localhost:9200/_nodes/process?pretty

#output
"nodes" : {
    "kQgZZUXATkSpduZxNwHfYQ" : {
      "name" : "node-1",
      "transport_address" : "10.70.3.48:9300",
      "host" : "10.70.3.48",
      "ip" : "10.70.3.48",
      "version" : "2.2.0",
      "build" : "8ff36d1",
      "http_address" : "10.70.3.48:9200",
      "process" : {
        "refresh_interval_in_millis" : 1000,
        "id" : 1650,
        "mlockall" : true
      }

Run the cluster

You need to start the elastic deamon or do ./bin/elasticsearch on all your nodes in the cluster

Test the status of cluster

Test the status of the elastic cluster.

[hadoop@CCLinDataWHD01 pliu]$ curl -XGET 'http://localhost:9200/_cluster/state?pretty'
{
  "cluster_name" : "hdfs_elastic",
  "compressed_size_in_bytes" : 334,
  "version" : 4,
  "state_uuid" : "5HNWvEDMSlyeG2yZ92acUQ",
  "master_node" : "F-aJixNFSIiSYp5N_IAeLQ",
  "blocks" : { },
  "nodes" : {
    "7j1T8NMSTque9lBcE1Pd-Q" : {
      "name" : "node-2",
      "ephemeral_id" : "ai9NiqoRQSaU1qa8UfMufQ",
      "transport_address" : "10.70.3.49:9300",
      "attributes" : { }
    },
    "F-aJixNFSIiSYp5N_IAeLQ" : {
      "name" : "node-1",
      "ephemeral_id" : "qs5yizBvSOaec-SBcSrO7Q",
      "transport_address" : "10.70.3.48:9300",
      "attributes" : { }
    },
    "t6U8Kf_NSQSnsmY4tmNWKA" : {
      "name" : "node-3",
      "ephemeral_id" : "_okE5-fzRyK8VXlhSxwLIQ",
      "transport_address" : "10.70.3.50:9300",
      "attributes" : { }
    }
  },
  "metadata" : {
    "cluster_uuid" : "Sono_FJpRM6Q4T31H6qKDg",
    "templates" : { },
    "indices" : { },
    "index-graveyard" : {
      "tombstones" : [ ]
    }
  },
  "routing_table" : {
    "indices" : { }
  },
  "routing_nodes" : {
    "unassigned" : [ ],
    "nodes" : {
      "t6U8Kf_NSQSnsmY4tmNWKA" : [ ],
      "F-aJixNFSIiSYp5N_IAeLQ" : [ ],
      "7j1T8NMSTque9lBcE1Pd-Q" : [ ]
    }
  },
  "snapshot_deletions" : {
    "snapshot_deletions" : [ ]
  },
  "snapshots" : {
    "snapshots" : [ ]
  },
  "restore" : {
    "snapshots" : [ ]
  }
}

Date : 16/09/2014

Participants : NS,PV

Ordre du jour

Précédente réunion le 25/06/2014

Déploiement de TranSMART, bioMAJ, WWWblast et Galaxy

Retour de congrès et futur congrès

Futurs développement PT6 : iRODS, MIDAS, LIMS, eCRF.

Mise en place d'une forge pour le LIMS et formalisation du projet LIMS

Mise en place d'OpenStack

Les stations de travail des bio-informaticiens.

Règles d'utilisation des machines virtuelles.

Est-ce qu'on peut utiliser OwnCloud pour récupérer des données non génomiques?

Etude comparative des ETL ?

Commentaires et actions

En attente d'une discussion avec l'équipe OpenStack du CC-IN2P3 le 22/09/2014 | NS

RAS | NS

Réunion au sujet de KitWare/Midas le 19/09/2014 | NS

Pierre va discuter avec Jacques pour mettre en place une forge et intégrer le projet LIMS | PV

Discussion le 22/09/2014 avec le CC. Attention à reparler de la prestation SysFera à ce moment-là! | NS+PV

Expliquer l'intérêt d'OTRS pour formaliser leurs demandes lors de la prochaine réunion Bio-info.

Fixer les règles en réunions bio-info, les écrire dans le Wiki et les communiquer au chef de plateau. Faut-il que les plateaux recensent eux-même leurs machines? | NS

Poser la question à Jacques | NS

Analyser les workflow du PT2 pour déterminer quelles parties pourraient être intégrée dans un ETL | PV

Réunion du 31 Août 2017

Personnes présentes

CD

JHA

YM

PDU

PV

Ordre du jour :

Bilan stage JHA

Champs dynamiques

Validateurs champs dynamiques

Résumé

Bilan stage JHA

JHA nous a présenté sa soutenance. Quelques points ont été discutés et sont a retravailler. Dans l'ensemble les objectifs du stage ont été remplis.

L'équipe NoE remercie JHA pour son implication dans le projet et lui souhaite bon courage pour la suite de sa carrière.

Champs dynamiques

Nous avons reçu les retours de 2 binomes sur 3 de la NET. Ces retours ont été analysés, discutés et inclus en format JSON dans NoE.

Il nous manque le retour du binome BB/KL qui va etre relancé.

A la suite de cela il faudra croiser ces données avec les entêtes des colonnes des templates de références construit par JHA. L'objectif est d'avoir un concordance supérieure ou égale à 80%.

Du coté code, la construction à la volée des champs dynamique lorsqu'ils existent est fonctionnelle. Ceux-ci arrivent dans un deuxième (et dernier) formulaire de création.

Pour rappel, lors de l'édition d'un échantillon les champs “type d'échantillon” et “origine” sont en lecture seule afin de rester sur les mêmes champs dynamiques.

Validateurs champs dynamiques

Les champs dynamiques étant construits à la volée, il faut également construire à la volée les validateurs associés.

On distingue plusieurs type de validateurs : champs obligatoire, valeurs possibles définies dans une liste, valeur minimum, valeur maximum.

Ces informations se retrouve dans l'architecture du JSON créé pour cet effet. Elles se retrouvent également au final dans le champs Sample.dyn_json.

La mise en place de ces validateurs est en cours.

Extend disk space of a vm in centos7

1. Increase the physical volume

Open VMware or virtualbox setting of the VM, choose the disk and increase the size to your desired size. Boot up your vm, you need first alter the physical volume of your partition.

# Normally, your linux has a /dev/sda, you should have the following lines by typing 
$ lsblk
           sda               8:0    0  200G  0 disk 
            ├─sda1            8:1    0    1G  0 part /boot
            └─sda2            8:2    0  39G  0 part 
                ├─centos-root 253:0    0   37G  0 lvm  /
                └─centos-swap 253:1    0    2G  0 lvm  [SWAP]
                
# You can notice the sda partition has 200G, but sda2 use only 39 G. We want to increase sda2 from 37G to  199G. 

To do this, there are three steps to make:

alter your partition table so sda2 ends at the end of disk

reread the partition table (will require a reboot)

1.1 - Alter the Partition table

# Open the disk partition management tool  
$ fdisk /dev/sda

# 1. Issue p to print your current partition table and copy that output to some safe place. 
# 2. Issue d followed by 2 to remove the second partition. 
# 3. Issue n to create a new second partition. Make sure the start equals the start of the 2nd partition table you printed earlier. Make sure the end is at the end of the disk (usually the default).
# 4. Issue t followed by 2 followed by 8e to toggle the partition type of your new second partition to 8e (Linux LVM, In Linux , LVM(Logical Volume Manager) provides the facility to increase and reduce the file system size.).
# 5. Issue p to review your new partition layout and make sure the start of the new second partition is exactly where the old second partition was. If everything looks right, 
# 6. Issue w to write the partition table to disk. 

# You will get an error message from partprobe that the partition table couldn't be reread (because the disk is in use).

1.2 Reboot your system

This step is necessary so the partition table gets re-read.

2. Resize the LVM

# After your system rebooted invoke
$ pvresize /dev/sda2

# Now you should see your sda2 has 199G
$ lsblk
           sda               8:0    0  200G  0 disk 
            ├─sda1            8:1    0    1G  0 part /boot
            └─sda2            8:2    0 199G  0 part 
                ├─centos-root 253:0    0   37G  0 lvm  /
                └─centos-swap 253:1    0    2G  0 lvm  [SWAP]
# Now, we can create or extend logical volumes to use the free space which are not assigned. 
# In our case,the partition centos-root under /dev/sda2 has 37G. We want to extend it to 197G 

2.1 Resize the LVM

# 1. Check available space. 
$ vgdisplay centos
# 2. Use lvextend command to increase the size. 
$ lvextend -L +160G /dev/mapper/centos-root
# 3. Finally perform an online resize to resize the logical volume. 
$ xfs_growfs /dev/mapper/centos-root

Remove a LV or reduce disk volum of a LV in Centos7

Here we are going to see how to reduce the Logical Volumes. Everyone says its critical and may end up with disaster while we reduce the lvm. Reducing lvm is really interesting than any other part in Logical volume management.

Before starting, it is always good to back up the data, so that it will not be a headache if something goes wrong.

To Reduce a logical volume there are 5 steps needed to be done very carefully.

While extending a volume we can extend it while the volume under mount status (online), but for reducing we must need to unmount the file system before reducing.

Let’s wee what are the 5 steps:

unmount the file system for reducing.

Check the file system after unmount.

Reduce the file system.

Reduce the Logical Volume size than Current size.

Recheck the file system for error.

Remount the file-system back to stage.

In this tutorial, we will reduce the LV /dev/pengfei_test/pengfei_manager, which we created in Setup Flexible Disk Storage with Logical Volume Management (LVM) in Linux.

1. Umount the file system

# check the mounted file system
df -h

# umount the file system
umount -v /mnt/manager/

# if you can't umount, because it's busy, use the following command to check which process are using it.
lsof +f -- /home


# check errors in the file system
e2fsck -ff /dev/pengfei_test/pengfei_manager

e2fsck 1.42.9 (28-Dec-2013)
Pass 1: Checking inodes, blocks, and sizes
Pass 2: Checking directory structure
Pass 3: Checking directory connectivity
Pass 4: Checking reference counts
Pass 5: Checking group summary information
/dev/pengfei_test/pengfei_manager: 11/1179648 files (0.0% non-contiguous), 118098/4710400 blocks

# Must pass in every 5 steps of file-system check if not there might be some issue with your file-system.

2. Reduce the file system

# reduce the file system size. here 10 G is the size of file system after reduce. which
# means we reduce 8G
resize2fs /dev/pengfei_test/pengfei_manager 10G

# reduce the lv size
lvreduce -L -8G /dev/pengfei_test/pengfei_manager

WARNING: Reducing active logical volume to <9.97 GiB.
  THIS MAY DESTROY YOUR DATA (filesystem etc.)
Do you really want to reduce pengfei_test/pengfei_manager? [y/n]: y
  Size of logical volume pengfei_test/pengfei_manager changed from <17.97 GiB (575 extents) to <9.97 GiB (319 extents).
  Logical volume pengfei_test/pengfei_manager successfully resized.

# check your new lv size
$ lsblk

pengfei_test-pengfei_manager   253:3    0   10G  0 lvm 

# Re-size the file system back. In this step if there is any error that means we have messed-up our file-system.
resize2fs /dev/pengfei_test/pengfei_manager

3. Mount back the file-system

If everything goes well, now you can mount back the file system

# 
mount /dev/pengfei_test/pengfei_manager /mnt/manager/

# check the new size of your file system
df -h
/dev/mapper/pengfei_test-pengfei_manager    9.7G   37M  9.2G   1% /mnt/manager

# we can also check our vg if they took back the 8G
lvdisplay pengfei_test
 

4. Remove a LV

# umount the lv
umount /mnt/manager

# Open fstab, remove the automount line, otherwise, it will not reboot again !!!
vim /etc/fstab

# remove the LV
lvremove /dev/pengfei_test/pengfei_manager

# use lsblk, or lvs to see the new list of lvs

5. Common problems

5.1 Wrong fstab config results to reboot fail

1. If your vm can boot in safe mode, with a root password you can get a prompt. Then just delete the bad lines in your /etc/fstab

2. If your vm can only get a grub prompt, you need to do the following

1. At the grub prompt, hit a to append options
2. add init=/bin/bash to the end of the kernel command line and press enter
The system will boot to a prompt like 'bash-3.2#' enter the following commands at the prompt

3. mount -o remount, rw / --target /
4. vim /etc/fstab
edit the fstab file commenting the errors by adding a # at the begining of each problematic line, save the file

5. reboot by pressing CTRL+ALT+DEL

Réunion du 06 Avril 2017

Personnes présentes

CD

JHA

YM

PDU

PV

Ordre du jour :

[CD] : Faudrait commencer l'internationalisation de NoE (mettre locale dans routing + fichier de traduction appelé dans le twig)

[CD] : Je propose de MàJ le mock up suite aux derniers changements + création du fichier secret.py (non versionné) secret.dist.py (versionné) et versionnage de settings.py

Présentation des ontologies par JHA

Travail autour des classifications reçues (on ne sort pas de la salle tant qu’on a pas deux consensus proche d’une version 1, prévoyez des vivres et de l’eau si jamais vous avez peur de manquer.)

Résumé

Présentation sur les ontologies par JHA

JHA nous a présenté quelques ontologies de référence, leur schéma de construction, qui les utilisait, leur fréquence de mise à jour ainsi qu'un tableau final comparatif.
Elle nous a aussi fait découvrir un web service très intéressant d'exploration d'ontologies : Bioportal
Cela nous a permis de pouvoir nous orienter vers SNOMED CT lors de la deuxième partie de la réunion.
Slides ici : M:/02_DST/04_UTEC/06_UTEC/Projets/En cours/NoE/2017_Stage_Julie/presentations/

Discussions et consensus autour des classifications rendues par la NeT

Il s'avère que les classifications proposées par les experts ne sont pas toutes à la hauteur de nos exigences attendues.
Après quelques tentatives de merge infructueuses à partir des quelques exemples fournis nous avons décidé de nous orienter vers une ontologie de référence connue et reconnue : SNOMED CT. (pour information : c'est une norme aux US et bMx l'utilise depuis plusieurs années)
Dans un premier temps et pour la V1, l'idée n'est pas d'aspirer l'intégralité de SNOMED CT, mais de s'en inspirer fortement pour les quelques nœuds qui nous intéressent et toujours aussi à partir de ce que la NeT nous à fourni.
Cela nous permettra de pouvoir évoluer vers un Full SNOMED CT si cela s'avère nécessaire par la suite sur des versions ultérieures de NoE.
Découpage de l'aspiration des données pour le consensus classification Bioentity :

JHA : Noeud Bactérie

CD : Noeuds Parasite et Plasmide

YM : Noeuds Virus, Champignon, Mammifère, Oiseau

Deadline : lundi 10 avril 2017.
TODO ensuite :

Consensus de classification Sample en suivant le même protocole

Faire suivre les deux consensus à la NeT pour validation finale et passage dans les équipes.

Donner le go pour les prochains devoirs de la NeT, réexpliquer si besoin.

Autres points listés par CD

Pas traités lors de cette réunion, à remettre à l'ordre du jour de la prochaine.